<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tt xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2006/04/ttaf1"  
xmlns:tts="http://www.w3.org/2006/04/ttaf1#styling">
<head>
<styling>
<style id="1" tts:textAlign="right"/>
<style id="2" tts:color="transparent"/>
<style id="3" style="2" tts:backgroundColor="white"/>
<style id="4" style="2 3" tts:fontSize="20"/>
</styling>
</head>
<body>
<div xml:lang="en">
<p begin="0:00:00" dur="00:00:17.00">This piece of music is a love song to the city of Florence.  It’s called &lt;i&gt;Salve flos Tusce gentis&lt;/i&gt; or &lt;i&gt;Hail Flower of the Tuscan People&lt;/i&gt; and was written in about 1436.  It’s a motet, a multi-voiced sacred composition.</p>
<p begin="0:00:17" dur="00:00:23.00">Its lyrics in Latin show the composer’s great affection for the city and especially, its ladies. The women are likened to strong, beautiful mythological figures like the love goddess Venus. This homage might also be a disguised hymn of praise to the Virgin Mary.  She was considered the source of creation and inspiration and the protector of the arts. </p>
<p begin="0:00:40" dur="00:00:17.00">The man who showed such a passion for Florence was French composer and musician Guillaume Dufay.  This is just one of the many pieces he wrote in the city’s honour — and one of the masterpieces of the Renaissance.  The text, in English, is on the screen of this audio point. </p>
<p begin="0:00:57" dur="00:00:43.00">Translation:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Hail, flower of the Tuscan race, Florence, hail.&lt;br&gt;Hail, great glory of Italian soil;&lt;br&gt;Hail, happy mother who begets so many learned offspring,&lt;br&gt;So many men of excellent counsel and faith,&lt;br&gt;So many who are distinguished for their admirable integrity,&lt;br&gt;So many who are distinguished for their piety.&lt;br&gt;</p>
<p begin="0:01:40" dur="00:00:30.00">Hail, you to whom are beholden all that is honourable in art,&lt;br&gt;All that is knowledge, all that is eloquence.&lt;br&gt;Hail, you whose fame is spread throughout the world,&lt;br&gt;Who raise up and send your children to the stars.&lt;br&gt;Now I have sung, and my melodious voice has been appreciated,&lt;br&gt;Your favours and your merits have not perished together.</p>
<p begin="0:02:10" dur="00:00:30.00">I am weary, but my voice is not tired of singing,&lt;br&gt;That you may live who are to be sung in my poems.&lt;br&gt;Now hail to you, O maidens, splendour of Tuscany:&lt;br&gt;So thinks my soul, and I do not remain here without love.&lt;br&gt;They stand at the gates like nymphs; they are like naiads,</p>
<p begin="0:02:40" dur="00:00:38.00">Or Amazons, or provocative Venuses.&lt;br&gt;Any man burns with their embraces and their sweet kisses.&lt;br&gt;As soon as a man sees them, he falls in love.&lt;br&gt;Goddesses of the world, yours for all ages,&lt;br&gt;I have sung your praises: I, Guillaume, who was born at Fay. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Supported by an award from the Arts and Humanities Research Council.</p>
</div>    
</body>
</tt>
