<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tt xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2006/04/ttaf1"  
xmlns:tts="http://www.w3.org/2006/04/ttaf1#styling">
<head>
<styling>
<style id="1" tts:textAlign="right"/>
<style id="2" tts:color="transparent"/>
<style id="3" style="2" tts:backgroundColor="white"/>
<style id="4" style="2 3" tts:fontSize="20"/>
</styling>
</head>
<body>
<div xml:lang="en">
<p begin="0:00:00" dur="00:00:13.00">Several sculptures in this room depict images of the dead Christ. They were meant to elicit feelings of pity and sorrow in everyone who saw them — a reminder of Christ’s sacrifice for humanity.</p>
<p begin="0:00:13" dur="00:00:11.00">This song also focuses on the intense emotions surrounding the death of Jesus. Its lyrics are quite graphic describing the body of Christ hanging on the cross:</p>
<p begin="0:00:24" dur="00:00:09.00">‘to free us from original sin&lt;br&gt;And to save us from damnation&lt;br&gt;He hangs, as you can see, upon the hard wood…’</p>
<p begin="0:00:33" dur="00:00:15.00">The piece, called &lt;i&gt;Se mai per maraviglia,&lt;/i&gt; or &lt;i&gt;If ever in wonder,&lt;/i&gt; was written by Franciscus Bossinensis, known as Francis of Bosnia. He wrote many pieces for lute and voice, and this is one his most famous and moving compositions.</p>
<p begin="0:00:48" dur="00:00:21.00">This recording was made by the Royal College of Music especially for the Medieval & Renaissance Galleries. The text, in English, is on the screen of this audio point. You can also download the complete track free from the V&A's website, www.vam.ac.uk.</p>
<p begin="0:01:09" dur="00:01:51.00">Translation:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;If ever in wonder raising your face&lt;br&gt;To the clear sky you think, o blind people&lt;br&gt;Of that true lord of paradise&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Turn your eyes over here, that is presented to you&lt;br&gt;Not that form oh my not that pain&lt;br&gt;That will contemplate knots of laments</p>
<p begin="0:03:00" dur="00:01:40.00">Weep for the great sorrow of the world&lt;br&gt;Weep for the bitter death and the cruel suffering&lt;br&gt;If the spirit of compassion pierces your heart&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;To liberate us from the ancient deception</p>
<p begin="0:04:40" dur="00:01:16.00">He hangs as you see on the hard wood&lt;br&gt;And to save us from perpetual damnation.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;This recording was made by the Royal College of Music and was supported by an award from the Arts and Humanities Research Council.
</p>
</div>    
</body>
</tt>
