<?xml version="1.0"?>
<div xml:lang="en">

    <p begin="0:00:00">Suspended above this audio point is a vaulted ceiling decorated with scenes painted in fresco on plaster. The term ‘fresco’ means that images were painted directly onto fresh plaster.  The pigments combined with the plaster, fixing the image.</p>
    <p begin="0:00:16">This ceiling once spanned a small square chamber in Cremona, in Northern Italy and was painted in about 1500 by a local artist, Alessandro Pampurino.  It is slightly over 4 metres, or 12 feet, in diameter and shaped like an umbrella.</p>
    <p begin="0:00:33">It’s divided into eight panels, each occupied by a circular medallion containing a painting of one of the female Muses of classical mythology. The Muses are painted to look like classical sculpture.</p>
    <p begin="0:00:47">Each of the eight panels containing the Muses is separated by vertical ‘ribs’ painted with palmettes – fan-shaped leaves on a blue background with gilded wooden studs.  The ribs smooth out towards the centre of the ceiling where there is a focal point, a trompe l’oeil oculus.  An oculus is normally a circular opening to the sky in the top of a dome.</p>
    <p begin="0:01:10">Here, though, the oculus is painted in realistic colours.  An elderly man, a young woman and a small boy peer down as if they were looking into the room from the top of the dome.  The woman holds her hand to her ear as if listening to the music of the Muses below her.  Above their heads, a white fluffy cloud floats in a blue sky.</p>
    <p begin="0:01:33">Immediately beneath the painting of the woman and child is the panel showing the Muse of Sacred Song, Polyhymnia.  Like all the Muses, she’s shown as a beautiful young woman with flowing tresses that fall below her knees.  She wears a loose, belted shift and carries a set of pan-pipes.</p>
    <p begin="0:01:51">Clockwise from Polyhymnia’s panel is Clio, Muse of History, with a swan at her feet; Euterpe, Muse of Music and Lyric Poetry, with her double flute; Melpomene, Muse of Tragedy, playing a curved horn; Thalia, Muse of Comedy, playing a lira de braccia, a stringed instrument resembling a violin;</p>
    <p begin="0:02:12">Erato, Muse of Love Poetry, with a tambourine; Terpsichore, Muse of Dance and Song, playing a viol; and finally Urania, Muse of Astronomy.  She carries a compass and holds a globe aloft in her left hand.</p>
    <p begin="0:02:27">Semi-circular spaces beneath the panels are filled by ten lunettes – half-moon shaped panels.  Two larger lunettes opposite one another are painted with pictures of Apollo, the god of Poetry and Music, and Calliope, the Muse of Epic Poetry, who blows a long trumpet.</p>
    <p begin="0:02:46">The others depict the heads of six Roman emperors and two of their womenfolk, set in pairs facing each other in profile. Their identities, however, are not certain.</p>
    <p begin="0:02:56">Although small, the room this ceiling adorned was clearly important. With its fashionable decoration and its references to the arts, it was used by a select few for private, intellectual pursuits – reading, discussion and perhaps the performance of music.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt; Supported by The Band Trust.</p>

</div>
